# Yiqian Liu

- • - • Vancouver, BC

https://www.linkedin.com/in/yiqian-liu/

## Curriculum Vitae

#### **RESEARCH INTERESTS**

Obtained degrees in Computer Science and Mathematics, I am a working Data Scientist with published paper, filed patent, and various experience of machine learning and R&D projects. **Computer vision** is my most recent focus, as demonstrated by the personal project on object recognition with YOLO. I also found computer graphics interesting. Autonomous vehicles (ambulances) and diagnoses aided by computer graphics or image analyses are the two applications that I care the most.

#### **EDUCATION**

### Master of Computer Science, thesis option

2013 - 2016

University of New Brunswick

Fredericton, NB

Thesis: Machine Learning for Wind Power Prediction. Supervisor: Huajie Zhang

Relevant Courses: Machine Learning & Data Mining, Foundations of AI, Computer Graphics

#### **Bachelor of Science in Mathematics**

2009 - 2013

Shandong University

Jinan, China

Visiting Student at Loughborough University, England, 2012 – 2013

## **PUBLICATIONS**

Yiqian Liu, Huajie Zhang, "An Empirical Study on Machine Learning Models for Wind Power Predictions", Proceedings, 15th IEEE International Conference on Machine Learning and Applications (IEEE ICMLA), Dec. 2016.

• Attended conference and presented poster in Anaheim, California, USA, December 18-20, 2016.

#### **RESEARCH & WORK EXPERIENCE**

Senior Data Scientist	Mar 2022 – Present
Mastercard	Vancouver, BC
Software Developer/Data Scientist	May 2017 – Feb 2022
Fortinet	Burnaby, BC
<b>Software Developer</b> (Co-op with UNB) IBM	Jan – Aug 2015 Fredericton, NB

#### SELECTED PROJECTS

## Bridge Hand Recognizer

2022, Personal

Playing card detector for contract bridge based on YOLO [GitHub]

- Prepared training data from scratch by taking card photos, programmatically combining with different backgrounds, and using OpenCV to virtually adjust lighting, etc.
- Refined and re-sampled training data based on discrepancies of evaluation results among classes to improve performance iteratively.

• Trained models with cloud resources to recognize 52 classes with 99% precision.

## Labeling Frauds with Limited Ground Truth

2022, Mastercard

Label generator for optimizing weights of anomaly scores for passive biometrics identity model

- Proposed, experimented, and documented strategies involving data extraction, cleaning, and labeling.
- Ran controlled experiments to identify most influential factors for model performance.
- Filed patent on new labeling methods.

#### **Ensemble Classifier for Malware Detection**

2021, Fortinet

Accuracy-focused model built on features from multiple engineering teams, achieving reduced dependencies and better data interaction

- Identified & corrected data quality issue by visualizing hundreds of binary features during EDA.
- Prevented data leakage by consulting data source owners and building solid validation pipeline.
- Stacked on less correlated predictions from linear, tree-based, and deep learning models.
- Achieved at least 95% performance of rule-based team of 30+ malware analysts.

### **Anomaly Detection in Network Traffic**

2019, Fortinet

Open-ended project to discover best approaches to detect abnormal patterns in second-level network traffics

- Applied feature engineering tricks before running clustering algorithms to deliver instant values.
- Further built probability distribution-based detector according to academic papers.

## **Machine Learning for Wind Power Predictions**

2016, UNB

Empirical study of nine machine learning regression models for predicting wind energy

- Collected and merged data from 3 distinct sources to prepare 7 datasets for training & evaluation.
- Designed and conducted experiments to evaluate effects of different structures of DNNs.
- Applied cross-validation and statistical test in order to compare model performance.
- Concluded by visualizing and bench-marking that SVM was best of nine.

## Image Segmentation with Parallel k-means

2014, UNB

Project for graduate course Parallel and Distributed Processing

- Parallelized k-means clustering with OpenMP for image files in C/C++ according to past research.
- Compared results for different iterations, k's, and local minima.
- Wrote formal report in format of IEEE Journals.

## OTHER RELEVANT R&D PROJECTS

Ranking File Execution Info with TF-IDF Techniques	2019, Fortinet
Finding Related Malwares with Graph Database and Cosine Similarity	2018, Fortinet
Malware Segmentation with Text Clustering	2018, Fortinet
Titanic Data Visualization [Visualization   Code]	2016, Udacity
Research Report on GIB: an Adversarial Search Algorithm for Contract Bridge	2014, UNB
Interactive Rubik's Cube Simulation [Cube   Recorded presentation]	2014, UNB

#### RELEVANT SKILLS AND TRAINING

Programming Languages Python, SQL, JavaScript, Java, C/C++

Frameworks & Libraries pandas, scikit-learn, NumPy, SciPy, Matplotlib, OpenCV, imgaug

Spark, TensorFlow,

Other git, Bash

## OTHER TRAINING

Image Processing with Python Track Data Analyst Nanodegree Time Management 2020, DataCamp 2017, Udacity 2015, Mitacs

## MISC INFO

Volunteering: Recommendation system for Canoo (ICC) • Mastercard Changeworks (CanadaHelps)

Languages: English, full professional • Chinese Mandarin, native Hobbies: Photography (instagram.com/liuyq983/) • Contract bridge